Finding Aid for Dean C. Worcester Papers 1887-1925
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dean C. Worcester papers 1887-1925
Worcester, Dean C. (Dean Conant), 1866-1924.
1 oversize folders
4.4 linear feet
86354 Aa/2, Ac
University of Michigan professor of zoology and museum curator, participated in or and led several research expeditions to the Philippines, member of the First and Second Philippine Commissions and involved in several Philippines business ventures; records includes notes, correspondence, publications and photographs relating to research expeditions, service on Philippines Commissions business activities, of special interest are notes of a trip taken to Mindoro and Palawan in July of 1910 and papers pertaining to the special Wood-Forbes Investigating Mission to the Philippines in 1921.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated in 1957 by Alice Worcester Day (Mrs. Kenneth B. Day). Mrs. Day was Dean C. Worcester's daughter. Donor no. 3253
The collection is open for research.
Worcester Chronology
1866 Born, Thetford, Vermont
1887-1888 Visited the Philippines with Joseph Beal Steere expedition sponsored by the University of Michigan
1889 Graduated from the University of Michigan
1890-1893 Visited the Philippines as leader of the Menage expedition sponsored by the Minnesota Academy of Natural Science
1893 Appointed instructor at the University of Michigan
1895 Promoted to assistant professor of zoology and appointed curator of the University Museum, University of Michigan
1898 Published The Philippine Islands and their People
1899 Appointed to the First Philippine Commission, visited the Philippines with the commission, and supervised compilation of commission's final report
1900 Appointed to the Second Philippine Commission and returned to the Philippines
1901 Appointed Secretary of the Interior in the Philippine Commission's government of the Philippines
1913 Resigned position with the Philippine Commission and became vice-president of the Philippine-American Company
1914 Published The Philippines Past and Present
1913-1924 Worked at various business enterprises in the Philippines
1924 Died in Manila
Dean Conant Worcester was born in Thetford, Vermont, the youngest son of an impoverished family of nine children. In 1884, his older brother and sister paid his expenses to the University of Michigan where he majored in zoology and came under the influence of Joseph B. Steere, chair of the Department of Zoology. In 1887, still an undergraduate, Worcester joined Steer's expedition to the Philippines, financing the costs by insuring his life and borrowing on the policy.
The Steere expedition was recognized as a scientific success. With academic credit for his participation in the expedition and a semester's work in zoology, Worcester obtained his A.B. degree in 1889. He and Frank Bourns, also of the Steere expedition, planned a longer sojourn in the Philippines and found financing through the University of Minnesota and a wealthy Minneapolis businessman Louis F. Menage. The Menage Expedition, 1890-1893, resulted in the collection of over three thousand specimens of birds, bats, butterflies, reptiles, mammals, corals, shells and in ethnological material. Upon his return, Worcester married Nanon Fay Leas and in the autumn of 1893 became an instructor in animal morphology at the University of Michigan. He began publishing monographs on Philippine birds, with Bourns and alone, and in 1895 he was promoted to assistant professor of zoology and appointed curator of the Zoological Museum.
In 1897 Worcester delivered his first general public lecture on the Philippines to the Unity Club of Ann Arbor and in that same year published his first general article on the Philippines, "Spanish Rule in the Philippines, co-authored with Bourns. With Dewey's victory over the Spanish in Manila Bay (May 1, 1898), Worcester began to think of the exciting prospect of the Philippines as an American colony. During a six week period, July 10 to September 1, 1898, Worcester wrote a very successful book The Philippine Islands and Their People, based on the letters he had written home during his scientific expeditions. A few months later, and as the McKinley government moved to extend American military control over the Philippine archipelago, a letter from his expedition colleague Frank Bourns warning of the danger of a Philippine insurgency led him to seek a meeting with President McKinley at which time he presented Bourns' views and augmented them with his own. McKinley asked Worcester to join a "civilian commission composed of men skilled in diplomacy and statesmanship" as requested by Admiral Dewey who was alarmed at the rejection by the newly declared Filipino government of the U.S. program of benevolent assimilation.
Through his participation in both the First and Second Philippine Commissions and in his position of Secretary of the Interior in the Commission government from 1901 to 1913, Worcester continued to have great influence on the formulation and implementation of American policy in the Philippines. His tenure on the First and Second Philippine Commissions would be the longest of all the commissioners. Worcester's rejection of independence for the Philippines, first voiced in an 1899 interview with Dr. Apacible, a Philippine insurgent with whom Worcester met in Hong Kong on his voyage to the Philippines, would never waver.
In 1913 Worcester resigned his position with the Philippine Commission to become vice-president of the Philippine-American Company. The following year he published The Philippines Past and Present and continued to direct various business enterprises until his death. Worcester's influence on American colonial policy and the various and controversial roles he played in the Philippines from his first visit in 1887 to his death in Manila in 1924: scientist, government official, propagandist and entrepreneur, earned him both accolades and deep resentment.
The Worcester collection covers the period of 1900 to 1924 and has been arranged into six series: Correspondence; Papers; Articles, lectures, etc.; Newspaper clippings; Miscellaneous; and Photographs.
The Dean C. Worcester papers filed at the Bentley Historical Library consist of correspondence, subject files, newspaper clippings, publications, and photographs pertaining to his activities in the Philippine Islands. Of interest are notes of a trip taken to Mindoro and Palawan in July of 1910 and papers pertaining to the special Wood-Forbes Investigating Mission to the Philippines in 1921. The collection includes correspondence with William Howard Taft and Leonard Wood.
Subject Terms
Mindoro (Philippines); Palawan (Philippines); Philippines--History--1898-1946.; Voyages and travels.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Worcester, Dean C. (Dean Conant), 1866-1924.
Visual Terms
Americans--Philippines.; Anthropology.; Colonists.; Denby, Edwin, 1870-1929.; Dewey, George, 1837-1917.; Filipinos.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.; Philippines--History--Insurrection, 1899-1901.; Soldiers--United States.; Spaniards--Philippines.; Warships.; Worcester, Dean C. (Dean Conant), 1866-1924.
Contributors
Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927.
Genre
Caricatures.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence
  Correspondence dates from 1907 to 1922, unfortunately not the period of Worcester's early service in the Philippines. Although there is a letter from Secretary of War William Howard Taft in 1907 relating to the Philippine government and independence, the bulk of the correspondence pertains to Worcester lectures and to his book The Philippines Past and Present.
  - 1907-1911 (Box 1)
  - 1912 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1913 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1913 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1914 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1914 (Box 1)
  - 1915 (Box 1)
  - 1913-1915 concerning lectures, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1913-1922 concerning The Philippines Past and Present, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Papers
  Papers is a small series of files on specific topics. The files date from1910 to 1922 and concern such topics as the Wood-Forbes mission of 1921-22, disciplinary cases of government officials in 1911-1912, and Worcester's resignation from the Philippine Commission in 1913.
  - 1910 concerning a trip to Mindoro and Palawan (Box 1)
  - 1911-1912 concerning disciplinary cases of government officials, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1911-1913 concerning the production of a film on the Philippines (Box 1)
  - 1911-1913 include data used in writing The Philippines Past and Present (Box 1)
  - 1912 concerning attempts to transfer jurisdiction over the Philippine General Hospital to the University of the Philippines (Box 1)
  - 1912 concerning Gen. Henry Bandholtz (Box 1)
  - 1913 relating to Worcester's resignation from Philippine Commission (Box 1)
  - 1914 concerning speech by Winfred P. Denison, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1914-1925 concerning miscellaneous topics, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1921-1922 concerning Wood-Forbes mission to Philippines (Box 1)
- Articles, lectures, etc.
  Articles, lectures, etc. is a series that covers the period of 1898 to 1915. The materials all relate to affairs of the Philippine Islands.
  - Articles 1898-1915 and undated, concerning the Philippines, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Lecture 1910 given at the Y.M.C.A. (Box 2)
  - Lectures and speeches 1908-1913 and undated, concerning the Philippines, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Newspaper interviews 1899-1915 (Box 2)
  - Note cards (Box 2)
  - Report 1910 (Box 2)
    (extracts)
- Newspaper clippings
  The Newspaper clippings cover the years 1898 to 1915 with some gaps. The clippings are from both English and Spanish language newspapers and document Worcester's activities, speeches he gave, and reviews and assessments of his published studies of the Philippine Islands.
  - 1898 concerning The Philippine Islands and their People (Box 2)
  - 1899 accounts of speeches (Box 2)
  - 1913 concerning Worcester's activities in the Philippines, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - 1913-1914 concerning lectures (Box 2)
  - 1914 concerning lectures (Box 3)
  - 1914 concerning The Philippines Past and Present, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - 1899-1915 miscellaneous, 10 folders (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  Miscellaneous contains issues of the Annual Report of the Secretary of the Interior to the Philippine Commission, reprints of Worcester's articles on the Philippines, and collected articles and published materials.
  - Miscellanea (Box 3)
  - Plans for Worcester's Manila house 1915 (Folder Ac)
  - Annual Report of the Secretary of the Interior to the Philippine Commission, 1908, 1910-1913 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous printed material, including reprints of articles (Box 3)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series represent an accumulation of images documenting Philippine life and culture. Many of these photographs were used in Worcester's book The Philippines, Past and Present.
  - Philippines 1887-1893 (Box 4)
    - Agriculture (Box 4)
    - Artifacts (Box 4)
    - Botany (Box 4)
    - Geography
      - Guimaras (Box 4)
      - Jolo (Box 4)
      - Manila (Box 4)
      - Mindoro (Box 4)
      - Negros (Box 4)
      - Siquijor (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Industries (Box 4)
    - Native groups
      - Mangyans of Mount Halcon, Mindoro (Box 4)
      - Mangyans, Miscellaneous (Box 4)
      - Moros of Jolo (Box 4)
      - Spaniards and mestizos (Box 4)
      - Tagalogs of Mindoro (Box 4)
      - Tagbanuas of Palawan (Box 4)
      - Visayans of Negros (Box 4)
    - Zoology
      - Mammals (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Unidentified people (Box 4)
    - Unidentified places (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Duplicates, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Philippines 1899-1913
    - Current history
      - Insurrection
        - Caloocan (Box 4)
        - Fort San Antonio Abad (Box 4)
        - Imus (Box 4)
        - Malabon (Box 4)
        - Parañaque (Box 4)
        - Pasig (Box 4)
        - San Pedro Macate (Box 4)
        - Zapote River (Box 4)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
      - Manila scenes (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous persons
        - Americans (Box 4)
        - Filipinos, Spaniards, etc. (Box 4)
      - Philippine Commission (Box 4)
      - Spanish fleet wreckage (Box 4)
      - United States fleet (Box 4)
    - Flagellants at Balintawak (Box 4)
    - Industries
      - Fishing (Box 4)
      - Transportation (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Zoology (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Album, unidentified (Box 4)
  - Canada (Box 4)
  - Europe (Box 4)
  - Hong Kong (Box 4)
  - Japan (Box 4)
  - List of negatives taken in 1899, 1900 by Dean C. Worcester and P.L. Sherman (Box 5)
  - Illustration captions from Native Life in the Philippines (Box 5)
  - Illustrations (with captions)
    - From The Philippine Islands and their People (1898) (Box 5)
    - From The Philippines Past and Present (1914), 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (unidentified)
  - Portraits (Box 5)
Related Collections in other repositories
Dean C. Worcester papers and photographs are located in a number of other repositories. From information gathered by the Michigan Historical Collections and by the University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology, the following have been identified:
Rare Books and Special Collections, University of Michigan Libraries (711 Hatcher Library): 1700 items, including 24 volumes of correspondence and reports and 21 volumes of clippings. This collection is described in Balita mula Maynila, by Thomas E. Powers.
Thetford Historical Society, Thetford, Vermont: 10 linear ft.
Museum of Anthropology, University of Michigan (4th Floor, Ruthven Museums Building): 4,775 negatives.
Field Museum of Natural History, Chicago, Illinois: Between 5,000 and 10,000 negatives. These Worcester holdings are combined with several other collections of Philippine photographs.
Original prints of Worcester negatives are found in all the above collections, as well as in the Anthropological Archives of the U.S. National Museum, American Museum of Natural History, Peabody Museum of Harvard University, and Rautenstrauch-Joest Museum in Cologne, Germany.